Jaime Andrés Arau Pontones

+34657402968 / andres.arau@outlook.com Calle Granada 41, piso 604. Madrid, Spain. C.P 28007 https://www.andresarau.com/

Self-employed Data Science consultant with 10 years of experience in the design and implementation of household surveys, online dashboards, interactive maps, and MEL systems. My expertise lies on combining data science with MEL approaches in order to enhance learning and facilitate ongoing adaptation and accountability of development programmes. By having led several large-scale surveys internationally, I have also gained extensive expertise in training teams, quantitative analysis, and data visualisation.

INTERNATIONAL EXPERIENCE

Austria, Canada, Colombia, Cuba, Ghana, India, Kenya, Madagascar, Mexico, Mozambique, Nigeria, Peru, Sierra Leone, Spain, Sweden, United Kingdom, USA, Vietnam

EDUCATION

MSc. In Economic Development and Growth Lund University and Carlos III de Madrid	2012-2014
B.A. Honours in Economics with a minor in Global Studies University of Ottawa	2005-2009

PERSONAL SKILLS AND COMPETENCES

Languages	Spanish (native), English (fluent), Portuguese (basic)
Software & systems	ArcGIS, Google Maps, Google Sheets, HTML 5, KoBoToolbox, Leaflet, MS Excel, NVivo, Power Bi, R, Shiny R, Stata, Survey Solutions, Ubuntu, Zoho

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Independent Data Science Consultant & Associate at Oxford Policy Management

2019 - present

- Data visualization, GIS, and interactive dashboards;
- Design frameworks and digital systems to monitor large development programmes;
- Advice on survey implementation internationally;
- Build local capacity to robustly implement data collection exercises;

Consultant | Oxford Policy Management, Oxford Survey and data specialist:

2015 - 2019

- Design and implementation of large data collection exercises internationally;
- Development of system and real time dashboards for Data Quality Assurance of household surveys;
- Questionnaire design and CAPI programming.

Project Manager | C-230 CONSULTORES / FUNDACIÓN IDEA, Mexico City

2014 - 2015

- Evaluation design and econometric data analysis;
- Training and management of fieldwork teams for data collection exercises

Summer intern. Gender diversity unit | INTER-AMERICAN DEVELOPMENT BANK, Washington D.C.

2013

• Evaluation design and econometric data analysis

Monitoring and Evaluation Officer | THE HUNGER PROJECT, Mexico City

2009 - 2012

- Design and implementation of MEL Systems; and
- Design, implementation, and analysis of Participatory Rural Appraisals

Consultant | ASHOKA MÉXICO & CENTRAL AMERICA, Mexico City

2010 - 2011

- Evaluation design; and
- Training and management of fieldwork teams for data collection exercises

WORK AND PROJECTS THAT BEST ILUSTRATES MY SKILLS AND COMPETENCIES

	1
Mapping tool for assessing risk factors for severe COVID-19	2020-ongoing
OPM has been invited to join the Mozambican Scientific Advisory Group on COVID-19,	Mozambique
which aims at providing the Government with evidence-based advice on how to best	OPM/MOH
respond to the pandemic. My role was to use novel geospatial mapping techniques to	
provide the Government of Mozambique with information at the right spatial resolution	
http://andresarau.com/shiny/maprisco/	
Interactive map to track the location of 'health agents' trained on COVID19 prevention	2020-ongoing
OPM's MUVA programme has a cadre of young facilitators trained by the Ministry of	Mozambique
Health on the basic messaging for COVID 19 prevention. My role was to develop and	MUVA/OPM
interactive digital tool to monitor this nation-wide and t visualize where where these	
'agents' have been deployed. https://www.andresarau.com/shiny/agentesCovid	
Dashboard to Track Daily Reported Cases of COVID19 in Mexico	2020
A personal and voluntary project to provide citizens with the most up-to-date	Mexico
information on the evolution of the emergency in Mexico. The objective is to make	Volunteer work
official data more accessible to everyone and facilitate its visualisation.	
http://andresarau.com/shiny/covid19mx/	
Social and Economic impact Assessment of mutation breading projects under the RCA	2019-ongoing
Design, development and deployment of a data management system, including online	Austria
forms and dashboards, for the monitoring and evaluation of mutation breading projects	IAEA
implemented by the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA)	
Decentralized and Community Based Social Action (PROSAS)	2019
Design of fieldwork model and georeferenced data collection tools, training of local	Mozambique
teams and development of an interactive map to understand the coverage of social	UNICEF
protection services in Mozambique. https://mapa-social.com/	OTTICE
Evaluation of UK Partnering for Accelerated Climate Transitions (PACT)	2019 – ongoing
Design and implementation of results management systems and online dashboards to	Mexico, Colombia,
track the effectiveness of the programme's in enhancing actions and reducing climate	China
change in target countries. https://www.ukpactmel.com/	BEIS
Strengthening Local Development in the Highlands and Rainforest Areas Project (PSSA)	2019
Training of enumerators, program of CAPI questionnaires (Survey Solutions), and	Peru
development of quality assurance tools to ongoingly monitor an agricultural survey to	IFAD
assess the impact of PSSA on the livelihoods of Peruvian farming families.	IIAD
·	
Dural Canitation Ongrational Descarch (CLTC)	2010
Rural Sanitation Operational Research (CLTS) Management of the water and sonitation bousehold survey. CARL coding (Survey)	2019 Chana
Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey	Ghana
Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), design and implementation, training of enumerators, and a quality assurance	
Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), design and implementation, training of enumerators, and a quality assurance system for the survey.	Ghana UNICEF
Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), design and implementation, training of enumerators, and a quality assurance system for the survey. Rural Sanitation Operational Research (CLTS)	Ghana UNICEF 2019
Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), design and implementation, training of enumerators, and a quality assurance system for the survey. Rural Sanitation Operational Research (CLTS) Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey	Ghana UNICEF 2019 Malawi
Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), design and implementation, training of enumerators, and a quality assurance system for the survey. Rural Sanitation Operational Research (CLTS)	Ghana UNICEF 2019
Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), design and implementation, training of enumerators, and a quality assurance system for the survey. Rural Sanitation Operational Research (CLTS) Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey	Ghana UNICEF 2019 Malawi
Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), design and implementation, training of enumerators, and a quality assurance system for the survey. Rural Sanitation Operational Research (CLTS) Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), and design and deployment of quality assurance system for the survey.	Ghana UNICEF 2019 Malawi UNICEF
Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), design and implementation, training of enumerators, and a quality assurance system for the survey. Rural Sanitation Operational Research (CLTS) Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), and design and deployment of quality assurance system for the survey. Enhancing Diagnostics for DFID's Public Finance & Tax Department (PFTD)	Ghana UNICEF 2019 Malawi UNICEF 2019
Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), design and implementation, training of enumerators, and a quality assurance system for the survey. Rural Sanitation Operational Research (CLTS) Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), and design and deployment of quality assurance system for the survey. Enhancing Diagnostics for DFID's Public Finance & Tax Department (PFTD) Design and deployment of an online dashboard to monitor macroeconomic and public	Ghana UNICEF 2019 Malawi UNICEF 2019 United Kingdom
Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), design and implementation, training of enumerators, and a quality assurance system for the survey. Rural Sanitation Operational Research (CLTS) Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), and design and deployment of quality assurance system for the survey. Enhancing Diagnostics for DFID's Public Finance & Tax Department (PFTD) Design and deployment of an online dashboard to monitor macroeconomic and public finance data to more rapidly identify trends and risks affecting multiple countries, and to	Ghana UNICEF 2019 Malawi UNICEF 2019 United Kingdom
Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), design and implementation, training of enumerators, and a quality assurance system for the survey. Rural Sanitation Operational Research (CLTS) Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), and design and deployment of quality assurance system for the survey. Enhancing Diagnostics for DFID's Public Finance & Tax Department (PFTD) Design and deployment of an online dashboard to monitor macroeconomic and public finance data to more rapidly identify trends and risks affecting multiple countries, and to develop central policy responses.	Ghana UNICEF 2019 Malawi UNICEF 2019 United Kingdom DFID
Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), design and implementation, training of enumerators, and a quality assurance system for the survey. Rural Sanitation Operational Research (CLTS) Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), and design and deployment of quality assurance system for the survey. Enhancing Diagnostics for DFID's Public Finance & Tax Department (PFTD) Design and deployment of an online dashboard to monitor macroeconomic and public finance data to more rapidly identify trends and risks affecting multiple countries, and to develop central policy responses. Working to Improve Nutrition in Northern Nigeria (ORIE III) -Endline	Ghana UNICEF 2019 Malawi UNICEF 2019 United Kingdom DFID 2018
Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), design and implementation, training of enumerators, and a quality assurance system for the survey. Rural Sanitation Operational Research (CLTS) Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), and design and deployment of quality assurance system for the survey. Enhancing Diagnostics for DFID's Public Finance & Tax Department (PFTD) Design and deployment of an online dashboard to monitor macroeconomic and public finance data to more rapidly identify trends and risks affecting multiple countries, and to develop central policy responses. Working to Improve Nutrition in Northern Nigeria (ORIE III) -Endline Survey design and management, CAPI programming (Survey Solutions), training of	Ghana UNICEF 2019 Malawi UNICEF 2019 United Kingdom DFID 2018 Nigeria
Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), design and implementation, training of enumerators, and a quality assurance system for the survey. Rural Sanitation Operational Research (CLTS) Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), and design and deployment of quality assurance system for the survey. Enhancing Diagnostics for DFID's Public Finance & Tax Department (PFTD) Design and deployment of an online dashboard to monitor macroeconomic and public finance data to more rapidly identify trends and risks affecting multiple countries, and to develop central policy responses. Working to Improve Nutrition in Northern Nigeria (ORIE III) -Endline Survey design and management, CAPI programming (Survey Solutions), training of enumerators and set up of quality assurance protocols and systems. The evaluation	Ghana UNICEF 2019 Malawi UNICEF 2019 United Kingdom DFID 2018 Nigeria
Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), design and implementation, training of enumerators, and a quality assurance system for the survey. Rural Sanitation Operational Research (CLTS) Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), and design and deployment of quality assurance system for the survey. Enhancing Diagnostics for DFID's Public Finance & Tax Department (PFTD) Design and deployment of an online dashboard to monitor macroeconomic and public finance data to more rapidly identify trends and risks affecting multiple countries, and to develop central policy responses. Working to Improve Nutrition in Northern Nigeria (ORIE III) -Endline Survey design and management, CAPI programming (Survey Solutions), training of enumerators and set up of quality assurance protocols and systems. The evaluation aimed to assess the effect of ORIE at improving the nutritional status of children in	Ghana UNICEF 2019 Malawi UNICEF 2019 United Kingdom DFID 2018 Nigeria
Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), design and implementation, training of enumerators, and a quality assurance system for the survey. Rural Sanitation Operational Research (CLTS) Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), and design and deployment of quality assurance system for the survey. Enhancing Diagnostics for DFID's Public Finance & Tax Department (PFTD) Design and deployment of an online dashboard to monitor macroeconomic and public finance data to more rapidly identify trends and risks affecting multiple countries, and to develop central policy responses. Working to Improve Nutrition in Northern Nigeria (ORIE III) -Endline Survey design and management, CAPI programming (Survey Solutions), training of enumerators and set up of quality assurance protocols and systems. The evaluation aimed to assess the effect of ORIE at improving the nutritional status of children in Northern Nigeria	Ghana UNICEF 2019 Malawi UNICEF 2019 United Kingdom DFID 2018 Nigeria DFID
Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), design and implementation, training of enumerators, and a quality assurance system for the survey. Rural Sanitation Operational Research (CLTS) Management of the water and sanitation household survey, CAPI coding (Survey Solutions), and design and deployment of quality assurance system for the survey. Enhancing Diagnostics for DFID's Public Finance & Tax Department (PFTD) Design and deployment of an online dashboard to monitor macroeconomic and public finance data to more rapidly identify trends and risks affecting multiple countries, and to develop central policy responses. Working to Improve Nutrition in Northern Nigeria (ORIE III) -Endline Survey design and management, CAPI programming (Survey Solutions), training of enumerators and set up of quality assurance protocols and systems. The evaluation aimed to assess the effect of ORIE at improving the nutritional status of children in Northern Nigeria Female Economic Empowerment in Mozambique (MUVA)	Ghana UNICEF 2019 Malawi UNICEF 2019 United Kingdom DFID 2018 Nigeria DFID 2017 – ongoing

future for disadvantaged young women in urban areas. Deployment of real time dashboards to monitor the implementation of projects. https://andresarau.shinyapps.io/education_project/	
Financial inclusion and women's empowerment in India's poorest states (PSIG)	2018
Design of systems and tools to assure the quality of a large household survey, build	India
capacity of local teams including enumerators and data managers. (Survey Solutions)	DFID
Integrated Dengue Early Warning System Driven by Earth Observations	2018
Survey specialist and design of MEL framework to evaluate the impact that early warning	
systems that use satellite climate forecasting technology have on reducing dengue	UNDP/UKSA
outbreaks in rural and urban Vietnam. (Survey Solutions)	on bir you on
Hunger Safety Net Programme II (HSNP II)	2017 - 2018
Survey design and management; design and implementation of an interactive dashboard	Kenya
to monitor and QA fieldwork; instrument design and CAPI programming; training of	DFID
teams (Survey Solutions)	
Kenya Programme Implementation and Beneficiary Satisfaction Survey (PIBS)	2017-2018
Design and management of a large-scale data collection to provide independent and	Kenya
rigorous data for the evaluation of PIBS. Development and implementation of a robust	World Bank
data quality assurance system for the survey. (Survey Solutions)	World Ballik
Living Standards Measurement Study (LSMS)	2017
Management of the Living Standards Measurement Study (LSMS) household survey,	Madagascar
including listing; CAPI coding (Survey Solutions); and design and implementation of a	World Bank
quality assurance system for the survey.	
Evaluation of the Child Development Programme (CDGP)	2017 and 2018
Survey manager and quality assurance expert for a cash transfer programme for	Nigeria
pregnant women and women with children under the age of two. The evaluation aims to assess CDGP's impact on maternal and child health. (Survey Solutions)	DFID
Sierra Leone Secondary Education Improvement Programme (SSEIP)	2017
Design and management of a large school survey, development of tools and interactive	Sierra Leone
dashboards to assure the quality of the data and the performance of the field teams. The	DFID
aim of the survey was to assess the impact of SSEIP on education outcomes. (Survey	
Solutions)	
Working to Improve Nutrition in Northern Nigeria (ORIE)	2015
Survey design and management, CAPI programming (Survey Solutions), training of	Nigeria
enumerators and set up of quality assurance protocols and systems. The evaluation	DFID
aimed to assess the effect of ORIE at improving the nutritional status of children in	
Northern Nigeria	
CaSalud	2014
Evaluation design and coordination of data collection strategies to assess a National	Mexico
intervention that aims to help solve three of the most pressing challenges in the field of	Carlos S. Foundation
Public Health in Mexico: chronic non-communicable diseases, maternal and child	
mortality, and prevention disease by age group.	
Climate Change and Indigenous People of the Amazon	2013
Evaluation design and extensive data analysis of a project aimed to promote training and	United States
	1.00
effective participation of indigenous communities in the process of consultation,	IDB

CONFERENCES AND SEMINARS

European Commission & Government of Cuba | Havana, Cuba

Lecturer at Seminar on Impact Evaluation

2016 and 2017

FELLOWSHIPS AND ADDITIONAL INFORMATION